Okay, so today's דף daf, *daf* is דף daf, י *daf yod*,
ten. And where do we pick up? We pick up at the
משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*. So we're a bit ahead thanks to our excellent
מגיד שיעור *maggid shiur* yesterday. Okay, so let's take a look. בית
שמאי Beit Shammai אומר *Beis Shammai omer*. So we're still over there
with our hens and roosters in our chicken coop. So yesterday the
whole issue was about moving the ladder from one to the next
and now let's take a look about designating because as you might
remember, the discussion at the beginning of the גמרא Gemara *gemara* was
whether the chicken was set aside for laying eggs or the rooster,
or whether it was set aside for eating. So here this משנה
Mishnah *mishnah*'s going to get to the point about most of the
chickens in your chicken coop are ones that you probably would not
plan on שחט *shecht*ing. The assumption of this משנה Mishna *mishnah* is
that rather than, because what never was discussed in the first discussion
in the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is, let's say you didn't set it
aside for either, what do we assume it's generally there for, what
would be its default assumption? And this משנה Mishna *mishnah* basically assumes
that the default assumption is, you're not presumed to say, oh, I'll
regularly take from my chickens and שחט *shecht* them. Generally, you wouldn't
be שחט *shecht*ing your chickens on a regular basis. So therefore actually
their default position is מוקצה muktzah, *muktzeh*, something you would not be
assuming you would actually take a chicken and שחט *shecht* it on
יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. So if you want to make
a chicken not מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh*, you have to designate it before
יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* or designate that you might that
these are a group of chickens from which you'll be taking specific
ones, and that's the issue that our משנה Mishna *mishnah* turns to.
So let's take a look. Okay, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai אומר
*Beis Shammai omer*, בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* says, לא lo יטול אלא
אם כן נענעם מבעוד יום *lo yitoll ella im kein nianam miba’od
yom*. Do not take, you cannot take from a chicken unless you
have moved it the day before. You've like picked it up and
moved and said I'm going to use this one tomorrow. ובית הלל
אומר *u’Beis Hillel omer*, עומד ואומר זה וזה אני נוטל *omed ve’omer
zeh vezeh ani notel*. בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* says you
can do it by standing off at a distance, you don't have
to pick it up and you can just point and designate this
is the one I'm going to use. But again, the point they
make here is you do have to designate. It's not assumed that
by default these things are not מוקצה muktzah, *muktzeh*, by default you
would not be using them. Okay, אמר amar רב חנן *amar Rav
Chanan*, says רב חנן בר אמי *Rav Chanan bar Ammi*, מחלוקת machloket.
בבריכה ראשונה *machlokes bivreicha rishona*.
The debate is by the first בריכה *breicha*, what's a I'm trying
to think of an English word for
בריכה *breicha*, it's each unit that of that's hatched by the hen.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* actually says that they normally hatch two at a
time and a male and a female, I don't know that because
I thought they laid one egg at a time.
Brood, that's the word. But again, anyway, so there's so the first
brood apparently what they would do would be is that they would
tend to not use that the first brood that was hatched they
would not usually take it and use it to שחט *shecht*. They
would use it to stick stay with the mother to help I
don't know her maternal instincts or something. So that would be the
chickens you generally would not take. דבית שמאי סברי *de’Beis Shammai savri*
and in that case, you have to designate them if you want
to take them and make them not מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh*. דבית שמאי
סברי גזרינן דילמא אתי לאמלוכי *de’Beis Shammai savri gazrinan dilma ati le’amluchay*,
and בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* says if you don't go ahead and
pick them up, then we're afraid that when it comes to be
יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* and you come to take it,
you'll change your mind because these are things that by default you
would much generally want to keep alive. ובית הלל סברי לא גזרינן
*u’Beis Hillel savri lo gazrinan*, בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* says
as long as you've verbally designated we're not afraid you'll change your
mind. That's by this first brood. אבל בבריכה שניה *aval bivreicha sheniya*,
but by the second brood and onward where it's a pretty regular
thing to be taking them and שחט *shecht*ing them when you need
it, דדברי הכל בעומד ואומר זה וזה אני נוטל סגיא Be'omed ve'omer
zeh vezeh ani notel sagia. *de’divrei hakol b'omed ve'omer zeh vezeh ani
notel sagiya*. Now not that they're not fundamentally not מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh*,
again, a normal chicken on a normal basis you wouldn't take, but
at least those it's a reasonable to be using them for that
and therefore the verbal designation is enough, we're not afraid you will
change your mind. So again the default is everything is מוקצה muktzah
*muktzeh*. Generally, you know, you can't normally you wouldn't סתם *stam* take
a chicken and שחט *shecht* it.
However, the issue about needing to pick it up is only by
the first brood where you might change your mind, the second one
it's a reasonable thing to be doing and you are not afraid
you'll change your mind. That's this approach. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
*gemara* says like this, where was we, אבל דדברי הכל בעומד וזה
אני נוטל סגיא *aval de’divrei hakol b'omed vezeh ani notel sagiya*. ובית
הלל למה לי למימר זה וזה אני נוטל *u’Beis Hillel lamah lei
lemeimar zeh vezeh ani notel*. Now the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, okay,
so we get that בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* wants you to pick
it up, handle it, make sure that you're comfortable with your decision
you won't change your mind. But בית הלל Beit Hillel. *Beis Hillel*
that says verbal designation is enough, why does it have to be
so specific? Why does it have to be this particular one I'll
take? לימא leima מכאן אני נוטל mikan ani notel, למחר *leima mikan
ani notel lemachar*. Why don't he can be more general? Why don't
he just say I'm going to take from some one of the
chickens or some of the chickens in the in this roost, in
this coop, right? Because that gives you a lot more latitude, right?
Why do you have to designate exactly this one? Just say I'm
going to take a chicken from here tomorrow.
Makes it sound like you have to be very specific. Now, וכי
תימא בית הלל לית להו ברירה, v'chi teima Beit Hillel leis leihu
breira. maybe the reason is that בית הלל Beit Hillel does not
hold of ברירה. breira. Right? What's ברירה? breira? ברירה Breira is that
you're not specific now,
later it becomes more specified what it was that you were like,
you know, which thing you want, and then we say retroactively it's
like you had always indicated that one. So meaning that would be
the idea. If I say, "I'm going to take from here tomorrow,
one of these things,"
you know, it's still not clear which one. You're going to wait
until tomorrow to retroactively figure out which is the one that you
were planning on taking. Okay, so maybe they don't hold
of it becoming meaningful retroactively or designated retroactively. Okay, now again, it's
a little bit interesting that you need the idea of ברירה breira
because you could have said like, even if I'm only going to
use one, I'm making all of them not מוקצה, muktzah right? By
I, you know, the fact that I'm planning on possibly using any
of them means that I am setting all of them aside for
possible use. Right? It doesn't, you get the point? Even if it
winds up that you only used one of the ten, they were
all not מוקצה muktza, because you basically before יום טוב Yom Tov
said, "I might want to use this and therefore I'm setting it
aside for possible use." But the גמרא Gemara somehow is saying that
if you're just saying מכאן אני נוטל, the way it would be
allowed to be general and then pick one later is that the
one you picked later would be winding up to be retroactively the
one you had always intended that you were going to use, and
that's the one that's not מוקצה, muktza. and the one you didn't
wind up using even though you had said I'll take from among
these would still be מוקצה. muktza, Okay, so it's funny why the
גמרא Gemara has to assume that way, why you can't have the
idea of designating it for possible use. But that's sort of what
the גמרא Gemara is assuming. And therefore, maybe that won't work because
maybe you won't be able to retroactively say you meant a particular
one. And if your statement remains general, then it would be a
problem.
So מוקצה muktza. is a specific thing though, item by item. In
other words, a specific thing. You have to specify discrete items.
Yeah, but isn't it enough to say that among I'm not,
look, whether you have to proactively say I'm מכין meichin it, or
whether you have to say that's the only things I'm pushing away
from me. Either way, you could say I am setting aside this
group of ten chickens to pick from among them. These are chickens
then? This group, no, I don't care, call it ten entities. This
chicken I might use tomorrow. I want to have it ready for
possible use. This chicken I might use tomorrow. I want to have
it ready for possible use. Even if I'm going to not wind
up using it, it shouldn't be מוקצה muktza because I want it
to be available for potential use. It's sort of like the גמרא
Gemara before about ספק. safek. Who the heck cares about ספק safek
if the reality is that you want to למעשה lema'aseh use it
or you want to have the possibility of use? But for some
reason this גמרא Gemara, is assuming that if you need to hold
of ברירה, breira, so the only way you can be non-specific and
make something not מוקצה muktza, or make something מוכן muchan is if
later when you specify we say, well, that's always the one that
you had indicated initially that you were going to use. It's sort
of like this idea before of this issue of ודאי vadai versus
ספק, safek, which is funny because why can't the possibility be enough?
But that's the גמרא's Gemara assumption. Okay.
וכי תימא בית הלל Beit Hillel לית להו ברירה. breira. Now you'll
say בית הלל Beit Hillel doesn't hold of ברירה. breira. Okay, maybe
that won't work to say retroactively and therefore you have to be
specific. That's not true, I'll show you they hold of ברירה. breira,
והתנן, ve'hatnan, we taught in a משנה. Mishnah, This is a משנה
Mishnah in אהלות. Ohalos. המת בבית, hamet babayit, there's a dead body
in the house. ופתחים הרבה, ufetachim harbeh, and there are a lot
of doors in the house. Now the הלכה halacha is, there's a
principle called סוף טומאה לצאת. sof tumah latzet. In the end, where
will the טומאה tumah go out of?
Right? Because you all know the הלכה halacha with your house. Yeah,
I'll make like a real house.
Here's your dead body.
Okay. So you all know the I don't know what that is.
Okay. That looks like a centipede. Anyway, you all know the הלכה
halacha that, okay, here's your dead body. You all know the הלכה
halacha that the טומאה tumah hits the roof and goes to everything
under the roof, right? Now, there's another הלכה halacha as well, which
is that if there's a lot of doors to this house and
I get my sweat hands on these pens anyway, okay, there's a
door here and, you know, there's a door here, there's a lot
of doors. Now, once you open a door, well, okay, the טומאה
tumah goes out but nothing happens because there's no roof. But let's
say there's an overhang around the whole house. Okay. So if you
actually open a door, right, the טומאה tumah will go
out, it'll hit the roof and spread to everything under the roof,
okay? Now, let's say there are this way actually, it'll spread under
because there's the same overhang, but let's say they're distinct overhangs. Okay.
So what happens if now, that's once you open the door. But
there's a הלכה halacha called סוף טומאה לצאת. sof tumah latzet. And
the הלכה halacha of סוף טומאה לצאת, sof tumah latzet, where the
טומאה tumah will eventually go out of means even while the door
is closed, if this is the door you're going to be taking
the dead body out of, it's like it's already open. So even
before opening it once you designate or configure... which is the door
that's going to be taken out of, it's like it's already open.
And if somebody is standing here, even if the door is closed,
it's like it's open, and if there's an overhang, that person becomes
טמא. tamei. Okay, that's called סוף טומאה לצאת. sof tuma litzet. In
the end where the טומאה tuma will go out of. So let's
take a look. המית בבית, hamet babayit, there's a corpse in the
house ולו פתחים הרבה, velo petachim harbe, there are a lot of
doors in the house. And again, there's like overhangs over each door.
כולם טמאים. kulam tmeim. So since you might take it, they're all
closed doors, but since you might take the טומאה tuma out, the
body out of any door, they're all considered potential סוף טומאה לצאת.
sof tuma litzet. And therefore underneath the overhang over the door, it's
all טמא. tamei. It's like all of them because it might be
any one of them, it's like it's all of them.
נפתח אחד מהם. niftach echad mehem. Now one of the doors is
open and the rest remain closed. הוא טמא וכולן טהורין. hu tamei
vechulan tehorin. Then that one, now that it's open, that becomes the
one that's presumed to be the one that the body will go
out of. And the other ones are presumed to not be the
one. So the other ones under, you know, the overhang by the
other doors is טהור. tahor. It's only the one that's open. That
becomes identified as the one it will go out of, which saves
the other doors. Now let's say they're all closed וחישב להוציאו באחד
מהם. vechishav lehotzio be'echad mehem. You just planned in your mind. You
didn't open a door. You just thought in your mind, oh, I'm
going to take it out of the front door. או בחלון שיש
בו ארבעה על ארבעה, o bechalon sheyesh bo arba'a al arba'a, or
you said I'll take it out of the window. Okay, which is
a funny thing, but okay, I'll take it out of the window.
Now if the window has a minimum of ארבעה טפחים arba'a tfachim
by ארבעה טפחים, arba'a tfachim, that's considered a big enough size to
be considered a size that can be a פתח petach for removing
the מת. met. So all the doors are closed, but you just
indicate or think that you'll take it out of one of them.
So in that case, מצלת על כל הפתחים כולם. matzelet al kol
hapetachim kulam. The one that you've planned to take it out of
is considered to be the one and therefore the טומאה tuma goes
out of that door, even if the door is closed, but the
other doors are saved because they're not the one that it's going
to be taken out of. Okay, straightforward enough. Now נפתח אחד מהם.
niftach echad mehem. Let's say one of them opened. Okay, it's not
that it was already open. It opened after, you know, it started
off they were all closed and one of them just opened up.
I don't know, the door like swung open. So הוא טמא וכולן
טהורין. hu tamei vechulan tehorin. Did I just read... I reread myself.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I reread that. Okay. מצלת על כל הפתחים
כולם. matzelet al kol hapetachim kulam. בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim,
בית שמאי says והוא שחישב להוציאו עד שלא ימות המת. vehu shechishav
lehotzio ad shelo yamut hamet. When is it that planning to take
it out of one door saves the other doors? If you planned
before the person died. Okay, because then we could say that is
identified as the door and the other doors don't get that potential,
that designation. ובית הלל אומרים, uBeit Hillel omrim, אף משימות המת, af
misheyamut hamet, even after the person has died. So the question is,
okay, this guy died. All the doors were, all the doors were
considered, oh, there it's glitching a little bit. All the doors were
considered potential סוף טומאה לצאת sof tuma litzet doors. Okay, and therefore
the overhang under any of the doors was טמא. tamei. Okay, that
was the story after the guy died. Now you went ahead and,
so this is בית הלל. Beit Hillel בית שמאי says if you
picked one door before the guy died, then when the guy died,
that's the door we focus on. But בית הלל Beit Hillel says
I would take even after the guy died. So what happened after
the guy died? He first died, under, outside of each door with
its overhang is טמא tamei because any door might be the one.
Then you said I'm going to take him out of this door.
So then, so then בית הלל Beit Hillel says oh, now these
doors are okay. So here's the question: Are these doors okay going
forward or are these doors okay even retroactively, למפרע? lemafrea? Because now
once you've picked one, we say even from the moment he died,
this will be identified as the door and the others are saved.
So we're first reading this that בית הלל Beit Hillel is saying
retroactive. Even if you pick the door after he dies, then it
says that it says that is always the door that was defined
as the door that he would exit, the others are not, and
the others never were a problem once one door was picked, the
others become retroactively always okay. And that's the principle of ברירה, breira,
yes.
So if it's retroactive, someone could be standing outside the closed door
under the overhang,
assume he's טמא tamei and then after you pick one
and then he leaves, right, and he doesn't even know that he's...
yeah, you'd have to find him and tell him. Exactly. You'd have
to find him and tell him. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. הא אתמר עלה. Ha itmar ala. So you think that
shows you that בית הלל Beit Hillel says that you hold of
ברירה, breira, that retroactively the other doors are okay. But one minute,
it was said on this, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לטהר את הפתחים
מכאן ולהבא. letaher et hapetachim mikan ule'haba. We're only saying this to
say that the other doors are okay going forward, not retroactively. בית
הלל Beis Hillel would not say retroactively the other doors are okay.
וכן אמר רבי יושיה, Vechen amar Rabbi Yoshiya, לטהר את הפתחים מכאן
ולהבא, letaher et hapetachim mikan ule'haba, only going forward. מכאן ולהבא אין,
mikan ule'haba in, from now forward yes, למפרע לא, lemafrea lo, not
retroactively. Okay, so according to this, בית הלל Beis Hillel does not
hold of ברירה, breira which is pretty amazing because, you know, there's
major debate of תנאים Tannaim about ברירה breira. and here we're saying
that בית הלל Beis Hillel doesn't hold of it, so I don't
know how another תנא Tanna could, but okay. בית הלל Beis Hillel
doesn't hold of ברירה. Breira, So one explanation is... so again, what's
our question? Why do you have to say this is the chicken
I'm going to take. Why can't you say I'll take some from
one of these? So the first answer is, well, maybe בית הלל
doesn't hold of ברירה, Breira, and therefore it's not good enough to
be not specific. Even when you pick it later, it won't... we
can't say that retroactively that was the one designated. This is working
with an assumption that to make it not מוקצה, muktza it has
to be specifically designated. So you can't be generic and pick it
later cause בית הלל won't hold of ברירה, Breira. and it won't
make it retroactively as though it specifically had been designated. That's answer
number one. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, ולעולם למפרע, Ve'olam
lemafre'a, you know what, בית הלל could say that the other doors
are saved retroactively, that he does hold of ברירה. Breira והכא היינו
טעמא, Vehacha hainu ta'ama, ודילמא... vedilma...
so that's what he says, he says it would be retroactively. So
then why is it that you have to say specifically which chicken?
Why can't you generically say one of these chickens and then retroactively
we'll know which one you designated? הכא היינו טעמא, Hacha hainu ta'ama,
here's the reason here, דילמא מטלטל ושביק מטלטל ושביק וקא מטלטל מידי
דלא חזי ליה, dilma metal-tel veshavik, metal-tel veshavik, veka metal-tel midi d'la
chazi leh, because who says you're going to be happy with the
first one that you pick? You
say tomorrow you go in and you pick a chicken, you say
oh I'll take this one, nah this one's a little scrawny and
you put it down, and you take a look look, nah this
one's got an injured leg or whatever, then you take the third
one, now you're happy. So what do we say? So again, assuming
that you have to be designated that it has to be specific
which one you designate, so that third one we now say oh
that's the one you picked, that's the one that always was not
מוקצה. muktza. So what was the story with numbers one and two?
They weren't the ones you picked, so they were
מוקצה, muktza
and you were handling מוקצה. muktza, So the reason you can't do
it is again assuming all of this assumes for whatever reason that
it's not enough to sort of be non-specific, to say from among
these, why isn't that enough to set the whole group aside because
maybe I'll take from them? But no, it assumes you have to
be specific about which one you're going to use and only that
is the not מוקצה muktza. one. That's why even if they hold
of ברירה Breira, they won't allow it because you might not be
happy with the first one, and then retroactively and then even when
you finally get to the one that's not מוקצה, muktza. you'll have
handled ones that will turn out to have been מוקצה muktza because
they won't be the ones you'll have picked.
Okay, even if they hold of ברירה, Breira every time he picks
up one and he picks up two then he picks up three,
ברירה Breira kicks in each time?
Yeah, but no, only ברירה breira, only picks up only kicks in
when it's the one that he winds up using. That's the one
he had designated, the one meaning he didn't say I'm going to
use the one that I the first one that I pick will
be the one I'm not making מוקצה. Muktzeh. You know, and if
you say why doesn't he just say anyone I might pick? Well
that's back to my question. Why do we have to be specific?
But the גמרא Gemara. is assuming you have to be specific.
Okay, דהא מרת Deha marta says the גמרא, Gemara בעומד ואומר זה
וזה אני נוטל סגיא. So the גמרא Gemara. says one minute, I
don't get it. If you're saying that בית הלל says you'll stand
at a distance and designate, that means that the person presumably is
not so finicky and is not you know if he's going to
be able to stand at a distance and say I'm going to
take this one and that one, it means that the person you
know is able you know doesn't have to inspect it before deciding
which one he's going to use. Here's a scenario where he'll decide
which one he'll use just by visual. So if that's true, why
are we afraid that when he picks it tomorrow he'll be finicky
and he'll be you know and he'll reject one? He's satisfied by
a visual inspection to determine which one he's going to use. גמרא
Gemara. says no no, you don't understand the dynamics here says the
גמרא. Gemara, הני מילי, Hani mili, that's true, מערב יום טוב. me'erev
Yom Tov. If we if you pick it on ערב יום טוב
erev Yom Tov and we force you to designate it, what's going
to happen? Meaning if we basically רש"י Rashi sort of fleshes this
out. רש"י says like this: If we say, you know, yes, you'll
think you know which one, but will you be happy with your
decision or not isn't necessarily true. But if we say the following,
you have to
visually identify it and once you identify it only that one is
מוקצה Muktzeh. the other... only that one is not מוקצה, Muktzeh, the
others are מוקצה. Muktzeh So what's going to happen? You'll identify it
on ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, you'll come on יום טוב,
Yom Tov you'll pick it, whether you're happy with it or not
it doesn't matter why, you're stuck with it. That's the only one
that's not מוקצה. muktza, So we're not saying that you won't get
you know you won't change your mind, you might change your mind
but if we mandate that you pick it and that you're stuck
with it, so you're stuck with it. So you can do it
visually. But if we say we're going to allow you to decide
tomorrow and not pick it today, then you might when you actually
handle it choose to change your mind. They're saying we're not saying
that when you pick it ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov you
won't want to change your mind on יום טוב, Yom Tov. you
might want to but you won't have a choice. So there we
can say verbal designation is enough, but we can't wait for you
to pick it till tomorrow because then you might actually wind up
changing your mind. אבל ביום טוב אסור, Aval be'Yom Tov assur, to
wait till tomorrow and to not designate it from beforehand, that's forbidden.
דזימנין דמשתכח שמני כחושים, Dezimnin demishtakach shemanei kchushim, sometimes the ones that
looked fat turn out to be skinny, וכחושים שמנים, ukchushim shemanim, and
the ones that looked skinny turn out to be fat, וקא מטלטל
מידי דלא חזי ליה, veka metal-tel midi d'la chazi leh, and you'll
wind up handling things that retroactively will turn out to have been
מוקצה muktza because they won't be the ones you'll have picked. So
the bottom line is that yes, we are afraid that once you
handle it, you will change your mind. So why don't we demand
that you handle it ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov when you're
making your choice? Because once you made your choice, you're stuck, so
you're not able to change your mind. But we won't wait for
you, we won't allow you to make your choice only on יום
טוב Yom Tov itself. אינמי Inamei זימנין דזימנין zimnin dezimnin דמשתכחי demishtakchi
כולהו kulhu כחושא, kachusha, here's another scenario. You'll, none of them will
meet your, all of them will appear to be skinny. None of
them will meet your standards. ושביק להו, V'shavik lehu, and you'll abandon
all of them. ואתי לאמנועי V'ati l'amnu'ei משמחת יום טוב. misimchat Yom
Tov. And therefore, if you don't wait till tomorrow, till יום טוב
to pick it, you'll come in tomorrow, you'll look at every single
one, you'll reject every single one, and you won't have a chicken
for יום טוב. But if you designate it ערב יום טוב, Erev
Yom Tov, even if when you get there it's skinny, you know,
you've already committed to your choice. You've already said, I'm going to
use this tomorrow. So even then when you come in and it's
not as great as you had thought it would be, psychologically you've
already committed this is the chicken that we're cooking tomorrow and you'll
wind up using it. So that's why you do it beforehand because
you do it beforehand, you're committed to your choice, you'll go through
with it. You won't choose another one. You won't move מוקצה. muktza
You wait till tomorrow, you might wind up using none or you
might wind up moving ones that you won't have used and that'll
be a problem of מוקצה. muktza. And all of this assumes, so
even with ברירה, we're not going to let you defer your decision
and all of this assumes that for it to be not מוקצה,
muktza it has to really be the one you use. You cannot
have that as a potential use, that's not enough. It has to
really be the one you wind up using. Okay, so that's the
case of designating. Now the next משנה Mishnah. moves on to the
case of you did designate and now you're not sure which is
the one you designated. So you can see we're having fun. זימן
שחורים, Zimmen shechorim, so you designated black ones, ומצא לבנים. u'matza levanim.
And then, when you came to get it tomorrow, these are the
only chickens in the roost, and you came tomorrow to get the
ones you had designated, and instead of black, they had turned, they
were white. So it's a pretty good indication they're not the same
one. לבנים ומצא שחורים, Levanim u'matza shechorim, or they were white and
you had designated white ones and it turned out to be black
ones. שניים ומצא שלושה, Shenayim u'matza shelosha, you designated two and now
there were three in that space. So clearly one of them is
not the one you designated. אסורין, Assurin, in that case, they're all
forbidden because at least one, if not all of them, are מוקצה
muktza and they're mixed up, as certainly in the last case. שלושה
ומצא שניים, Shelosha u'matza shenayim, let's say you designated three but then
you came on יום טוב and there were only two there. מותרין,
Muttarin, that's permissible because you assume that it's a subset. So you
assume one went away, but the two remaining are the ones that
you designated. All of this assumes that you don't have a like,
you know, you don't sort of have a clear way of recognizing
them. Okay. בתוך הקן ומצא לפני הקן, Betoch hakan u'matza lifnei hakan,
let's say you designated them inside the coop and then you found
them outside of the coop. So אסורין, Assurin, that's forbidden. Now that's
funny. Why don't you assume that it's the same one that went,
took a little walk outside? But once it's outside, maybe it's someone,
maybe it's a random chicken. Maybe it's not the one you designated.
So that's forbidden. ואם אין שם אלא הם, Ve'im ein sham ela
hem, but if those are the only ones around, there are no
other chickens in the vicinity, then הרי אלו מותרין, harei elu muttarin,
then even if it's outside of the coop, obviously you can assume
it's the same way. So a lot of this seems relatively obvious,
but the גמרא Gemara will say interesting things about it. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara פשיטא, Peshita, says the first
thing גמרא. Gemara If you set aside white and you found black,
or black and you found white, or you know, duh, it's obviously
not the same one. What's the חידוש? chidush? אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון
שזימן שחורים ולבנים,
kegon shezimmen
shechorim ve'levanim, והשכים ומצא שחורים במקום לבנים ולבנים במקום שחורים. ve'hishkim u'matza
shechorim bimkom levanim ve'levanim bimkom shechorim. So he reads the two cases
in the משנה mishna. as one case. The משנה mishna said if
you set aside black and found white, or set aside white and
found black. He says it's not 'or'. It's one case. You set
aside black ones over in this coop and white ones in this
coop. Okay, so and you set the black ones, the next day
were white, and the white ones the next day were black. So
it's both are the same case. So basically you had set aside
black and white and you found black and white but in the
reverse places. So it's a reasonable assumption to saying maybe they all
switched places and it's the same one. Okay. מה דתימא, Mah d'teima,
I might have thought, הני אינהו נינהו, hani inu ninhu, these are
the same ones, ואיספוכי איספך, v'isupechi isapech, and they've just reversed, you
know, they've all, they've switched parts with one another. So קמשמע לן
kamashma lan that you can't assume that. That if they were black
and now white, and white and now black, you can't just assume,
oh, they probably just switched places with one another. That's not a
legitimate assumption. Says the גמרא, Gemara קמשמע לן kamashma lan הנהו אזדו
לעלמא, hanach azdu l'alma,
once you say that they're no longer in their original location, then
you cannot assume that they're in the other place. Once you say
these left, והני, v'hani, these now ones that are white, what allows
you to assume they're the other white ones you designated? Maybe אחריני
נינהו, achrinei ninhu, maybe they're complete random ones. Okay, so it's a
reasonable point. Once it's not the where you designated and you have
to assume that they are some other chickens, you're not entitled to
assume they're the other chickens you designated. had happened to have designated
over in the other coop. Okay. קמא, kama, so that's the חידוש.
chiddush. לימא מסייע ליה לרבי חנינא. leima mesayei lei le'Rabbi Chanina. Now
the גמרא Gemara says, let this be a support to רבי חנינא.
Rabbi Chanina. דאמר רבי חנינא de'amar Rabbi Chanina רוב וקרוב הלך אחר
הרוב. rov ve'karov halach achar ha'rov. So he has an important question
about how do you deal with cases of prioritize determine what happened
and determine identity of things. And let's say you have two different
determinants of it. Something could have come from nearby, but the majority
of stuff out there in the world goes in the other way.
So for example, in this case, I don't really need the board,
but we can use the black and we can use the white
here for a visual aid. Use
black and white. Okay, so this is the coop that you had
designated the black for, this is the coop you designated the white
for. You came the next day and there was the opposite one
was in the coop. Okay, now where is it, so from this
one you found white one. Where is it more, where is it
more likely that those white ones came from? Did they come from
this neighboring coop? Or did they come from, you know, who knows,
all the random chickens that are in the farms, my farm and
other farms and so on. So if we go by, do we
go by רוב, rov, the majority of the chickens in the world?
Are they the two chickens from this coop, or the majority of
white chickens? Or even the majority of white chickens within a one
mile radius? Are they the chickens in this coop, or is it
X other chickens? Obviously the X other chickens, there's a hundred other
white chickens in a one mile radius. Okay, or a hundred foot
radius, or whatever. But which are the ones that are closest? The
ones that are closest are these. And if these are closest, and
these are מוקצה, muktza so right, am I going to assume, where
do I assume the chickens came from? Did they come from the
closest location? And then the non-מוקצה muktza. ones switched locations and they're
all okay, because those were the closest location. Or do I assume
that they came from the larger population of numbers and they came
from the מוקצה muktza population outside of the coops. So that's the
question of רוב rov versus קרוב. karov. Which what assumption do you
make of where they came from? So the גמרא Gemara is saying
this should support רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, because רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
says רוב וקרוב הלך אחר הרוב. rov ve'karov halach achar ha'rov. You
go by the majority. And here too we're going by the majority
of chickens that are out there, and not by the closest ones,
because the closest ones are not מוקצה. muktza So the גמרא Gemara
says no. כדאמר אביי בדף. ked'amar Abbaye be'daf. הכא נמי בדף. hacha
nami be'daf. As אביי Abbaye says as we'll see later, we're talking
about a case that there is a דף, daf, a plank. And
here too there is a דף, daf, a plank. What does that
mean? It means that outside of the coop, so you know like
in bird feeders, again, I'm talking from pretty much ignorance about these
things, but you know like in bird feeders they've got like a
place for the birds to like rest outside of the feeders. So
apparently, if outside of the coop you actually have like a דף,
daf, a plank, for chickens to rest on, so then other chickens
will come and from the outside world and just, you know, visit
as it were and rest on that דף, daf that plank. So
it's saying it's not true that the only nearby chickens are the
ones in the neighboring coop, the white ones that you designated. There
are a lot of white chickens that are in the immediate vicinity
as well that come and rest on that דף, that plank. So
you know, so maybe they don't they don't take home in that
coop, but nevertheless, it's not like the other white chickens are far
away but the majority. They also come and they spend time near
this coop, and therefore they're also קרוב. karov. So it's not really
קרוב karov versus רוב, rov, the מוקצה Muktzah. chickens are also קרוב.
karov. Is that clear? Yeah, so the good chickens are yes the
non-מוקצה Muktzah. ones are right next door and they live next door,
but the מוקצה Muktzah. ones also visit often, and therefore they're also
קרוב. karov. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. שנים
ומצא שלשה אסורים. shnayim u'matza shlosha asurim. If you have two and
you found three they're forbidden. And it just explains ממה נפשך. mimma
nafshach. Look, either way, make a, you know, it's whatever the scenario
is, אי אחריני נינהו ei achreini ninhu if all three are new
chickens, אחריני נינהו achreini ninhu then they're all new and they're מוקצה.
muktzah. ואי לא אחריני נינהו ve'ei lo achreini ninhu if they're not
all new, only one of them is new, האי איכא חד דאערב
בהו ha'ika chad de'itarav behu at least one of them is a
מוקצה muktzah. chicken is not the one you designated. So therefore it's
obviously they're all going to be a problem. Gets back to our
whole problem before about a mixture of
מוקצה and anyway they're all
forbidden. שלשה ומצא שנים מותרים. shlosha u'matza shnayim mutarim. If it's three
and you found two it's permissible because here we assume it's not
a brand new two, that one left and two remained. מאי טעמא?
mai ta'ama? What's the reason? הני אינהו נינהו. hanei inhu ninhu. We're
going to assume that the remaining two are from the original group,
וחד מינייהו אזל לעלמא ve'chad mineihu azal le'alma and only one of
them left, rather than assuming that all three left and two new
ones came. So the גמרא Gemara says you know that's an interesting
debate about what happens when you have a subset. Do you assume
that you lost one or that it's a completely new set. So
לימא מתניתין רבי היא ולא רבנן. leima matnitin Rabbi hi ve'lo Rabbanan.
Maybe this is רבי Rabbi and not the Rabbis who debate a
very similar scenario, not about chickens but about money. Let's take a
look. דתניא, de'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. beraita. הניח מנה ומצא
מאתיים. heniach maneh u'matza matayim. Let's say you set aside a מנה,
maneh, a hundred dollars of of of what do you call it,
of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money, thank you, and in a box.
Box and you came back and you found two hundred dollars in
the box. Okay, so there is an extra hundred dollars. So you
have to assume that that extra hundred dollars might not be מעשר
שני Ma'aser sheni money and therefore it might be חולין Chulin money.
So then you don't know which is the מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni
money and which is the חולין. Chulin. So what do you do
in that case? So חולין ומעשר שני מעורבין זה בזה, Chulin u-ma'aser
sheni me'uravin zeh ba-zeh, דברי רבי. Divrei Rebbi. So רבי Rebbi says
yeah, the first hundred you assume it is still there, this is
a new hundred, so you have to assume it is a mixture
of מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni money and חולין Chulin money and you
will have to deal with it appropriately. Okay, and there are ways
you can redeem it and transfer the קדושה Kedusha that only one
hundred has the קדושה Kedusha and so on. But there is a
mixture of a hundred מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni money and a hundred
חולין. Chulin. וחכמים אומרים, Vechachamim omrim, and the Sages say הכל חולין.
Hakol chulin. That
is pretty shocking. Even though you found an extra hundred, he says
look, since it is obviously something is there that is not the
original, the second hundred, we are just going to assume that somebody
came and took the whole original amount and put in a new
two hundred. So you could have actually, and if you have a
random money, you will assume it is חולין, Chulin, you won't assume
that it is מעשר שני. Ma'aser sheni.
The opposite case?
Well we are going to get to the same case. We are
starting with the opposite case. So that is a case when you
have got extra and one wants to assume the whole thing swapped
according to חכמים. Chachamim. Now if you said that by the chickens
it would just make more of a problem. If you started with
two and found three, if we are going to assume all three
are new, then they are all מוקצה. Okay, so the chickens either
way, either if one is new or all are new, they are
all מוקצה. That is the debate there. When it is a super-set,
when it is more than you started with, are you going to
assume you could maintain the base or it all got swapped out?
But now we are going to get to the case that we
are dealing with which is the sub-set case. Yes.
So this case of the money
is the leniency if you say it is חולין. Chulin. Right. But
with the bird it
is a stringency, it is all new. Correct. Okay, but that case
is the birds it wouldn't matter which way, either way it's forbidden.
But now we get to our case. Now הניח מאתיים ומצא מנה.
Hiniach matayim umatza mana. Let's say you left two hundred and you
found a hundred. So two hundred of מעשר שני. Ma'aser sheni. So
now it is going to be the same debate. מנה מונח ומנה
מוטל, Mana munach u-mana mutal, דברי רבי. Divrei Rebbi. רבי Rebbi says
one hundred was left and a hundred was taken away. You assume
that at least the hundred left is from the original group and
therefore it is מעשר שני. Ma'aser sheni. וחכמים אומרים, Vechachamim omrim, הכל
חולין. Hakol chulin. The rabbis are very lenient, at least in this
case they say it is all חולין. Chulin. They say if it
is different then you will have to assume that it was all
removed and this is totally different and it's a new hundred. Okay,
now again by the birds the rabbis would be strict because by
the birds if you went from three to two, they say once
you see a change you have to assume that it is completely
new. So then according to them it would all be מוקצה. Here
they are lenient, by the birds they would be strict. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says it seems like our משנה, which is lenient
in the case of three and two, is רבי Rebbi and not
the rabbis. It says no, אפילו תימא רבנן. Afilu tima rabbanan. Even
the rabbis would agree in our case it would be permissible by
the birds. Why is that? איתמר עלה, Itmar alah, it was said
on this, רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר דאמרי תרווייהו, Rebbi Yochanan ve-Rebbi Elazar
de-amri tarvaihu, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar both
say שאני גוזלות הואיל ועשויין לדדות. Shani gozalot ho'il ve-atzuyan lidatot. גוזלות,
Gozalot, I keep saying chickens, but גוזלות Gozalot are like pigeons. Anyway,
birds are different because
they walk, they hop around, they move on their own. Which means
what? It means when it started with two hundred and now there
is a hundred, what happened to the other hundred? Did it get
up and walk on its own? Right, it's like a parent saying
this cookie didn't get up and walk out of the jar on
its
own. So the hundred didn't walk out on its own. Somebody came
and took it. So if somebody came
and taking a hundred, they're going to take the whole two hundred.
I don't know, maybe they only need a hundred. But okay. But
you have an external conscious agent that is taking a hundred, they
will say they took it all and that this is a new
hundred. But in the case of the birds, the birds can get
up and walk on its own, not somebody external. So one bird
walked away and the other two remained. Okay, if it needed a
person to come, if the birds are all bound up in a
cage, and initially there were three in the cage and you came
back and you found two in the cage, the rabbis might say
it is a new two. A person had to come and if
a person gets involved, I'll say he took it all and these
are new ones. Okay, but if the birds are doing it themselves,
there they will agree that one left and two remained.
Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ולמה לי לשנויי
אלא שאני גוזלות הואיל ועשויין לדדות? Velama li leshunayei ella shani gozalot
ho'il ve-atzuyan lidatot? Why do I need to give that reason that
pigeons are different because they can walk on their own and therefore
one can walk away and the other two remain? דאיתמר עלה בהא
דרבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר, De-itmar alah be-ha de-Rebbi Yochanan ve-Rebbi Elazar, it
was said about the debate
of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar who both
gave the scenario that birds can walk on their own. But the
same רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar debate what
is the case of this issue with the money and the מעשר
שני Ma'aser sheni money. חד אמר בשני כיסין מחלוקת, Chad amar be-shnei
kisin machloket,
that the debate of do we assume that this is all new
money or not is when there are two separate pouches, each pouch
has a hundred dollars. That's where you can assume the hundred that
remains is the original hundred. אבל בכיס אחד, Aval be-kis echad, but
if all two hundred were in one pouch.
Everybody would agree that that if it was a 200 in one
pouch and you came back and found 100 in a pouch, everybody
would agree you assume this is a new pouch because the original
200 was all bundled together. וחד אמר Vechad amar so the whole
debate is two separate pouches. The other one says, no, בכיס אחד
מחלוקת, Bekis echad machloket,
the debate is when it's in one pouch, that's where there's a
position that says it's new. אבל בשני כיסים, Aval bishnei kisim, when
it's two pouches, דברי הכל מנה מונח ומנה מוטל, divrei hakol mane
munach umane mutal, in the case of two pouches, everybody would say
that you're left with that the 100 that's left is from the
original. Okay, so this is the question of, right? וחכמים Vechachamim say
this... you've got to admit וחכמים Vechachamim is a stranger opinion that
says that it was all... once there's a difference, you assume it's
all taken and it's all new. So the question is, are they
saying that in the case of one pouch? That makes more sense.
And maybe in the case of two pouches they would agree that
you're left with half of the original. That's one version. Or no,
maybe וחכמים Vechachamim say it even in two pouches, and if it's
in one pouch, then even רבי Rebbi would agree that this is
all new. So that's the debate of how to frame the מחלוקת.
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to let's see how this translates
to what the implications of this for the case of the birds.
So here's what the גמרא Gemara says. בשלמא למאן דאמר בשני כיסי
מחלוקת, Bishlama leman de'amar bishnei kisei machloket,
if you say the debate of רבי Rebbi and the rabbis is
it all new or does some remain is the case of two
pouches, so where, you know, one could be taken independent of the
other. So therefore רבי Rebbi would say in a case... וחכמים Vechachamim
would say even in the case of two pouches, we're going to
assume it's all new. היינו דאיצטריך לשנויי הכא שאני גוזלות
דעשויין
לדדות. Hainu de'itztarich leshunaye hacha shani gozalot de'asuyin ledadot. That's why it's
comparable to the case of the chickens, right? What's the chicken case
like? Is it like two pouches or one pouch? Right? You have
chickens in your coop. People, answer the question. One... no, wait. No,
chickens in your coop, right? Is it like everything is bundled together
or each thing is independent, like two pouches, right? Once one walks
away, the other stays. Right, there's no bundling together.
So when we said, look, וחכמים Vechachamim say
that it's all new, why by the
chickens do we say some of the original ones remain? So that's
a reasonable question if the וחכמים's Vechachamim position is by separate pouches.
Then it's similar to the birds, which are all independent. So why
by the separate pouches do they say it's all new and here
they say it remains? Oh, well birds walk by themselves. That makes
sense. Okay, that we're comparing the cases of separate pouches, if that's
the debate of the rabbis, if that's where the rabbis say it's
all new even in the case of separate pouches, we want to
know why don't they say the same thing by the chickens? And
we have to say because chickens walk by themselves. אלא למאן דאמר
בכיס אחד מחלוקת, Ela leman de'amar bekis echad machloket, but if the
rabbis say that no, we only say it's all new when it's
all one bundle. So if we only say it's new when it's
all one bundle, that's the only time, then there's an obvious reason
the chickens are different because the chickens are separate, right? So if
you say, אבל בשני כיסים דברי הכל מנה מונח ומנה מוטל, Aval
bishnei kisim divrei hakol mane munach umane mutal, but if you say
that even the rabbis will say that if there are different pouches,
then we agree that there's some of the original that remains, it's
not all new. השתא למה לי לשנויי לה, Hashta lama li leshunaye
lah, why do I need to make a distinction "oh birds walk
by themselves"? There's a more basic distinction: the rabbis themselves agree when
they're separate pouches. האמרת בשני כיסים לא פליגי, Ha amart bishnei kisim
lo peligi, you would say that the rabbis themselves would not argue
by separate pouches. Okay, so we're trying to figure out why is
the case of the money different than the birds? And we say
birds walk by themselves. But now the גמרא Gemara is saying is,
you only needed that answer if you said that the case of
the money even when they're separate pouches, the rabbis says it's all
new. Then you'd say why don't we say the same by birds?
But if by the case of the money they only say it's
new by one pouch, why do you need to say the birds
are different because they walk? The birds are different because they're independent,
and that's why it's not all new. אמר רב אשי הכא בגוזלות
מקושרין ובכיסי מקושרין עסקינן, Amar Rav Ashi hacha begozalot mekusharin uvekisei mekusharin
askinan, because you know what? When we said one pouch, that that's
when they say it's all new, we don't literally mean one pouch.
Because it would be then bizarre, the גמרא gemara says, for somebody
that would say that half is left. If it's all one pouch,
we should assume somebody took the whole pouch. So the case when
we say they're debating when it's all one pouch is really two
separate pouches that are like rubber banded together, tied together. And there
וחכמים Vechachamim say I'm going to assume you took the whole bundle
and put in a new hundred, and רבי Rebbi is going to
say you only took one of the two and left the other
one. So but we're not talking about literally one pouch. We're talking
about two pouches bundled together. So if that's the case, the rabbis
will say it's all new. So now we'll say, okay, but let's
say you had a similar case by birds. Let's say the case
of the birds were tied together, their legs were tied together. So
what would the rabbis say? If they say by two bundles tied
together it's all new when you have one remaining, by the... birds
tied together, why don't they also say it's one new, right? Because
you have one remaining. Somebody took the two, they were bundled, or
the two walked off together, they were bundled and this is a
new one. And that's where they say no, there's a difference because
a bundle of two little bundles of money pouches stay together better
than two birds that are tied together. Okay, so גוזלות gozalot מנתחי
mintchei אהדדי, ahadadi, birds separate from one another, they walk around and
therefore the knot that binds them together separates. כיסים kisim לא מנתחי
mintchei אהדדי ahadadi and the money pouches don't separate from one another.
So it still could be a difference. Why is the birds, why
are we lenient by the birds if there's some that are strict
by the money or there's some that say the money is all
new? So there's two reasons. Number one is that we're really not
treating the birds different, that really it's just a case of separate
units and everybody is lenient by separate units. Or we are treating
the birds different, but the difference is when they're bundled together. Money
that's bundled together stays together, birds that are bundled together do not
stay together. So even if you say it's all new by money
because it's bundled together, it would not be true by the birds,
there we would assume they separated. So רבי Rebbi אמר amar לך,
lach, now רבי Rebbi who said that even by the money when
it's bundled together it's half that remained, he would say back to
you: כיסים kisim נמי, nami, even by bundles of money pouches, זימנין
zimnin דמיאכל demiakhel קיטריהו, kitreihu, sometimes the knot wears away, rots away.
So even money pouches sometimes the two separate. And therefore I'm going
to say that the hundred left is the original hundred. Okay, so
bottom line is fascinating question. You started with two hundred or two
birds, you found one, do you assume it's from the original or
not? And the גמרא gemara basically says sometimes that's a debate of
רבי Rebbi and חכמים, Chachamim, but the basic reason of the חכמים
Chachamim that might say it's different is because A, when a human
agency is involved and comes and gets involved that sort of makes
a question about exactly what happened. And also B, how much is
it, did it start off as separate units or as one unit
or somewhere in between, two separate units bundled together, in order to
lead to our assumption of whether this is half of what began
or something completely new. And the case of the birds might be
different because they don't involve human agency and that changes it. And
therefore what happened could have happened sort of by itself. And also
in the case of bundling, they could have naturally broken the bond
that bundled them, which is less likely in the case of money.
Okay, so now we move up. בתוך betoch הקן hakan ומצא umatza
לפני lifnei הקן hakan עשרה. asara. You designated a chicken or whatever,
a pigeon in the, it's more likely pigeons, like we keep talking
about chickens but I'm thinking in my terms this is pigeons. Okay,
it's actually a picture. Yeah, I know. If you ever go to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and you look, whatever, at some of the
archaeological sites or whatever, particularly like from the חשמונאים Chashmonaim period, you
know, pigeon coops were like a major form of, like, major industry
apparently was pigeons because they required very little maintenance and it was
an easy way to provide meat and there was other things as
well that they, so anyway it was a very major industry. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara, says לימא מסייע mesayei ליה lei לרבי חנינא.
le-Rabbi Chanina. So this idea that it's outside of the pigeon coop
and it's forbidden because it might not be the original one,
so maybe this supports רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. This is what we
said before,
דאמר de-amar רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina רוב rov וקרוב ve-karov הלך halach
אחר achar הרוב. ha-rov. If it has to choose between majority and
what's close, you go by the majority. So obviously the closest place
this could have come from was inside of the coop and
therefore it would be the one you designated, but
there's still a majority of other pigeons out there and we're going
to have to assume this came from
one of those other pigeons.
So that shows
you
go by the majority, not by the קרוב. karov. So אמר amar
אביי Abaye בדף, bedaf, again we're talking about that there's a plank
in front of the
pigeon coop and therefore there are a lot of external chickens that
are also or pigeons that are also קרוב. karov. They come and
they rest on the, on this plank and therefore they're also קרוב.
karov. רבא Rava אמר בשני bishnei קינים kinim זו למעלה מזו zo
lemalah mizu עסקינן. askinan. We're talking about two coops, one above another,
ולא מיבעיא זימן בתחתונה ולא זימן בעליונה. velo mibaya zimin betachtonah velo
zimin beelyonah. Now here's the case. You had a one coop, how
did they explain this, as a coop or as a section within
the coop? Tell me what word were they... they're translating it as
nests. Nests, right, I've been saying coop, but it really is nest.
So basically you've got, you know, I mean, again I'm not sure
exactly, but at least in some of these cases a columbarium, that's
what they're called, pigeon cotes, right, they have tiny little sort of
like little niches inside of them. That's a nice photo of them.
That's external, right, that shows you the דף on the outside, but
I mean inside they've also got like little holes for like each
separate pigeon. So basically here's what he says. You went ahead and
you designated a, you know, this is the עליונה, elyona, I don't
know what the heck, wait, anyway this is the עליונה elyona and
this is the תחתונה. tachtona. So you went ahead and you designated
in one and not the other. And then you found it in,
you designated one up here and then you found something down here
or vice versa. Let's take a look. So you have two nests
זו zo למעלה lemala מזו mizo one above another עסקינן. askinan. דלא
מיבעיא זימן בתחתונה ולא זימן בעליונה. delo mibaya zimin betachtonah velo zimin
beelyonah. Now let's say you designated a pigeon in the lower nest
and not in the upper one. ומצא בתחתונה ולא מצא בעליונה umatza
betachtonah velo matza beelyonah and you went ahead and you found in
the lower one and you did not find in the upper one.
דאסירי daasiri that it's forbidden. דאמרינן הנהו אזלו לעלמא והני אשתרבב ואשתרבב
ונחית. damrinan hanech azlu lealma vehani ishtarvuv veishtarvuv venachit. So hold on,
let me just check רש״י Rashi one second, one minute. One minute,
let me just check one thing. One minute, let me just check
one thing. Okay, so here's the case. You went ahead and you
had these two nests, okay, and you found... he's discussing the case
in the משנה where you didn't find in the nest, you found
in front of the nest. And you have these two nests, right,
and the question is, remember, the question in the גמרא gemara is
are we going by רוב rov or are we going by קרוב
karov and so on. So what רבא Rava is doing, everybody pay
attention, look, I need to explain this. What, the question is like
this, right, that you went ahead, the simple case is you designated
one in a nest and you found it outside and we have
to assume it's a different one. And the question is why do
we assume it's a different one, why don't we go by the
concern of קרוב, karov, why don't we, I mean, why don't we
assume קרוב, karov, the most likely place this came from was inside
of the nest, right? That was the question. Why don't we go
by קרוב, karov, why do we assume it's a random different one?
And the answer, one answer was well because there's a lot of
others that are קרוב, karov, there's a plank outside and therefore a
lot of other other other pigeons are also קרוב. karov. That was
one scenario. רבא Rava is going to say no, here's the scenario,
that's not the only thing that's קרוב. karov. This thing that's outside
on this plank and outside of the nest, it's, what was the
near, most nearby thing? You'll say the most nearby thing was inside
the nest. But there was another nearby thing, which was the nest
directly below it, right? It could have just as easily have come
from the nest below it and come up here as it could
have come from inside out. So he's answering the question why can't
we be lenient and say it's קרוב, karov, it came from nearby,
which means it came from the inside the nest and it's the
one you designated. And he's going to say because we have to
be concerned that it came from the nest directly above or directly
below, which is just as קרוב karov or at least within the
same קרוב karov category, enough that it won't make a difference. And
that's why we can't just assume it came from the inside. So
let's read that. So he says like this.
He says like this. רבא אמר בשני קינין זו למעלה מזו עסקינן.
Rava amar bishnei kinin zo lemalah mizu askinan. There are two nests.
ולא velo מיבעיא mibaya זימן ziman בתחתונה betachtona ולא velo זימן ziman
בעליונה. be-elyona. The one you designated was the bottom and not the
top one. ומצא בתחתונה ולא מצא בעליונה. umatza betachtonah velo matza beelyonah.
You found the pigeon in the bottom one, not in the nest,
but outside of the nest, and
no pigeon in the top one either. So there's two possibilities where
this came from, both of which are קרוב. karov. It could have
come from within the nest or it could have come from above
because the pigeon above is also missing and the one above is
מוקצה.
I understand, says מצא בתחתונה matza betachtonah not
מצא, matza, it means in front of the תחתונה, tachtonah, because that's
the scenario of the משנה. Okay, you have to go with that.
Okay, דאסרינן. daasrinan. That's forbidden. דאמרינן הנהו אזלו לעלמא, damrinan hanech azlu
lealma, both birds flew the coop, okay, והני אשתרבבו ונחית, vehani ishtarvuvu
venachit, and the one from the, or whatever, the bottom bird flew
the coop and the top one sort of came down and rested
in front of the bottom one. So the question is, isn't it
קרוב karov to assume it came from inside? And the answer is
no, maybe it came from a top nest and it came down.
That clearly would be a case where we would have to assume
it might be מוקצה. אלא אפילו זימן בעליונה ולא זימן בתחתונה. ela
afilu zimin beelyonah velo zimin betachtonah. But even in the reverse case,
you designated the one in the top nest and not the bottom,
and the same, but now the reverse scenario, ובא ומצא בעליונה ולא
מצא בתחתונה, uva umatza beelyonah velo matza betachtonah, and you went ahead
and you found the pigeon outside, it has to assume, outside of
the top one, but not, and no pigeon in the bottom one.
So again, where did this pigeon outside the top one come from?
Did it come from inside the top and therefore it would be
the one you designated and okay? Or did it come from the
one below? They're both roughly קרוב. karov. And he says even there,
we have to assume it's reasonable that it came from below. הנהו
נמי אסירי. hanechu nami asiri. That's also forbidden. דאמרינן הנהו אזלו לעלמא.
damrinan hanech azlu lealma. The one you originally designated flew
the coop. והני סרוכי סריך וסליק, vehani sruchi sreich vesalik, sort of
climbed up and went to the top coop. So even though it's
more natural for a pigeon to drop down than to go up,
but basic point is, the question is why can't we be lenient
and assume קרוב, karov, why do we assume רוב? rov? So either
yeah, in general we go by רוב rov other than קרוב, karov,
or... There's scenarios where there are other pigeons that are also קרוב
karov that this might be, either that there's a plank in front
so you get visiting pigeons that are also קרוב karov that it
might be and not from the one inside, or you have the
nest above or the nest below which is קרוב karov and it
might be coming from there. Yes?
So I was just going to say what's the אפילו? afilu? So
the אפילו afilu has to be the assumption is that it's more
likely for it to go down than to go up. Yeah, let's
just read to the משנה. אם אין שם אלו הן הרי אלו
מותרים. im ein sham elu hein harei elu mutarin. Now in all
these cases if there's... if these are the only ones around it's
permissible, presumably not in the case of the black and the white,
or in the two and the three because clearly those are new
ones. But in the case of, you know, inside the nest and
outside the nest, then if there's no other pigeons around, then you
can assume it's the same one. So the גמרא gemara says היכי
דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא במפורחין, iileima bimfurachin,
if it's birds that actually can fly at that stage, איכא למימר
הנך אזלו לעלמא והנך אחריני נינהו. ika lemeimar hanech azlu le'alma vehanech
achrini ninhu.
So who cares that there aren't any in the nearby vicinity? I
mean these birds fly. So it could still be a bird that
flew from somewhere
else. אלא במדדין. ela bimdadin. They're at the stage where they like
you know sort of waddle around, but they're not yet at the
flying stage. And therefore if there are no other ones, so meaning
if you designated a pigeon that was not yet... it couldn't fly
and you found and came and found another pigeon outside of the
nest that also couldn't fly, this one outside of the nest didn't
fly here, it's not at the stage that it could fly. So
if there are no pigeons in the nearby vicinity, right, so obviously
you have... you can assume it's the same one. אי ee so
now the גמרא says like this, אי דאיכא כאן בתוך חמישים אמה,
ee de-ika kan betoch chamishim ama, still says the גמרא, if there's
some other nest within fifty אמה, ama, about you know 75 feet,
אדודי אדדו, adudei adadu, אדדו, adadu, it could still waddle over from
a neighboring nest. The גמרא assumes that pigeons will travel fifty אמה.
ama. ואי דליכא כאן בתוך חמישים אמה, vee deleka kan betoch chamishim
ama, and if there is no nest within fifty אמה, ama, פשיטא,
pishita, it's obvious דמותר demutar that we don't assume they came outside.
Why? דאמר מר עוקבא בר חמא, de'amar Mar Ukva bar Chama, it's
interesting why it assumes a משנה is obvious based on a teaching
of an אמורא, amora, but מר עוקבא בר חמא Mar Ukva bar
Chama says כל המדדה אין מדדה יותר מחמישים אמה. kol hamadada ein
madada yoter mechamishim ama. When pigeons sort of walk around they don't
walk more than fifty אמה. ama. So A, we have to assume
the case is a not yet a flying pigeon, it's a walking
pigeon only. If that's true and then we're talking about none is
nearby means none is within fifty אמה, ama, it's not a big
חידוש. chiddush. So the גמרא says לעולם דאיכא כאן בתוך חמישים אמה.
leolam de-ika kan betoch chamishim ama.
Fine, we can say that there is another nest within fifty אמה.
ama. So why don't we have to assume maybe it came from
the other nest? וכגון דקיימי בקרן זוית. ukgon dekai bekeren zavit. It's
in... it's around the corner from your nest. מהו דתימא אדודי אדדו,
mahu diteitima adudei adadu, maybe it still wandered over from its home
nest, קמשמע לן כל היכא דמדדה והדר חזי לקניה מדדה. kamashmalan kol
heicha demadada vehadar chazi lekaanei madada. If it can walk and still
look back and see its original nest, it'll walk as long as
its home is still in sight. Okay? ואי לא לא מדדה. ve'ee
lo lo madada. But once it has to really leave home and
keep... you know its home is not in sight it won't walk
away from the home so far.
It won't fly the coop.
It won't fly the coop. So therefore that's what it's telling you
and therefore you don't have to assume that it came from elsewhere.